<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC '' 'reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
]>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-hardaker-dnsop-csync-FILLVERSION">
    <front>
    <title abbrev="Child To Parent Synchronization in DNS">
      Child To Parent Synchronization in DNS
    </title>
    <author initials="W.H." surname="Hardaker" fullname="Wes Hardaker">
      <organization>Parsons, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>P.O. Box 382</street>
	  <city>Davis</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>95617</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<phone>+1 530 792 1913</phone>
        <email>ietf@hardakers.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="FILLMONTH" year="FILLYEAR"/>
    <area>Operations and Management</area>
    <workgroup>DNSOP</workgroup>
    <!--
    <keyword ...>
    <keyword ...>
    -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies how a child can publish a record in
      its DNS zone that can indicate that a parental agent may copy
      certain records from the child zone.  They record may be
      monitored by a parental agent to either assist in or
      automatically transferring data between the child and
      parent.</t>

    </abstract>
    <!--
    <note ...>
    -->
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>This document specifies how a child can publish a record in
      its DNS zone that can indicate that a parental agent may copy
      certain records from the child zone.  They record may be
      monitored by a parental agent to either assist in or
      automatically transferring data between the child and
      parent.</t>

      <t>Some resource records (RRs) in a parent zone are typically
      expected to be in-sync with the data in the child's zone.  This
      is currently limited to NS and associated A and AAAA "glue"
      records.  Additionally, the children frequently have DNSKEY
      records which require corresponding DS record(s) in the parent.
      These records are referred to as "delegation records".</t>

      <t>It has been traditionally challenging for children to keep
      delegation records within a parent's delegation data current.
      This difficult usually derives from simple operator laziness or
      the complexities of maintaining a large number of DNS zones.
      Having an automated mechanism to update a parent's set of
      delegation records will greatly ease the maintenance burden of a
      child zone and improve the robustness of the DNS.</t>

      <t>This draft introduces a new RRTYPE ("CSYNC") that indicates
      which delegation records within a child should be copied into
      the parent's DNS zone data.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation" anchor="musts">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
	  "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
	  and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
	  described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Definition of the CSYNC RRType">
      <t>The CSYNC RRType contains as its RRDATA two components: an
      SOA serial number and a simple bit-list indicating the DNS
      RRTypes in the child that should be copied into the parent's DNS
      delegation records for the child.  Children wishing a parental
      agent to perform a synchronization MUST publish a CSYNC record
      at the apex of the child zone.  Parent agent implementations MAY
      choose to query child zones for this record and copy the data
      indicated by the bit field in the RRDATA of the CSYNC record
      according to the procedures listed later.  Parental agent's MUST
      process the entire set of child data requested (i.e., all record
      types indicated along with all of the records for that type) or
      else parent agents MUST NOT process any data records at all.
      Errors due to unsupported bits or otherwise nonpunishable data
      SHALL result in no change to the parent zone's delegation
      information for the child.  Parental agents SHOULD ignore a
      child's CSYNC RRDATA set if multiple CSYNC resource records are
      found; only a single CSYNC record should be expected.</t>

      <t>The parental agent MUST perform DNSSEC validation of the
      CSYNC RRTYPE data and MUST perform DNSSEC validation of any data
      to be copied from the child to the parent.  Parents MUST not
      process any data if any of the validation results indicate
      any anything other than "Secure" <xref target="RFC4034" />.</t>

      <section title="CSYNC record field values">
      </section>
      <section title="Operational Considerations">
      </section>
      <section title="Security Considerations">
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc1995;
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc2136;
      &rfc2845;
      &rfc3007;
      &rfc4033;
      &rfc4034;
      &rfc4035;
      &rfc4509;
      &rfc5011;
      &rfc5155;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc1611;
      &rfc1612;
      &rfc2182;
      &rfc3197;
    </references>
    <section title="Deployment Scenarios" anchor="deployment">
      <t>This appendix documents some additional deployment scenarios
	that have been traditionally difficult to manage.  They are
	provided as guidance to protocol developers as data points of
	real-world name server management problems.</t>
      <section title="Non-Standard Zones">
	<t>If an organization uses non-standard zones
	  (for example a purely-local TLD), synchronizing all the
	  name servers for these zones is usually a time-consuming
	  task.  It is made worse when two organizations with
	  conflicting zones merge.  This situation is not a
	  recommended deployment scenario (and is even heavily
	  discouraged) but it is, unfortunately, seen in the wild.</t>

	  <t>It is typically implemented using "forwarding" zones.
	  But there is no way to ensure automatically that all the
	  resolvers have the same set of zones to forward at any given
	  time.  New zones might be added to a local forwarding
	  recursive server, for example, without modifying the rest of
	  the deployed forwarding servers.  It is hoped that
	  a management solution which could handle the configuration
	  of zone forwarding would finally allow management of servers
	  deployed in this fashion.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Redundancy Sharing">
	<t>For reliability reasons it is recommended that zone
	  operators follow the guidelines documented in <xref
	    target="RFC2182" /> which recommends that multiple name
	  servers be configured for each zone and that the name servers
	  are separated both physically and via connectivity routes.  A
	  common solution is to establish DNS-serving partnerships:
	  "I'll host your zones and you'll host mine".  Both entities
	  benefit from increased DNS reliability via the wider service
	  distribution.  This frequently occurs between cooperating but
	  otherwise unrelated entities (such as between two distinct
	  companies) as well as between affiliated organizations (such as
	  between branch offices within a single company).</t>

	<t> The configuration of these relationships are
	  currently required to be manually configured and maintained.
	  Changes to the list of zones that are cross-hosted are
	  manually negotiated between the cooperating network
	  administrators and configured by hand.  A management
	  protocol with the ability to provide selective
	  authorization, as discussed in Section XXXFUTURE, would
	  solve many of the management difficulties
	    between cooperating organizations.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="DNSSEC Management">
	<t>There are many different DNSSEC deployment strategies that
	may be used for mission-critical zones.  The following list
	describes some example deployment scenarios that might warrant
	different management strategies.
	  <list>
	    <t>All contents and DNSSEC keying information controlled and
	    operated by a single organization
	    </t>
	    <t>Zone contents controlled and operated by one
	    organization, all DNSSEC keying information controlled and
	    operated by a second organization.</t>
	    <t>Zone contents controlled and operated by one
	    organization, zone signing keys (ZSKs) controlled and
	    operated by a second organization, and key signing keys
	    (KSKs) controlled and operated by a third organization.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>Although this list is not exhaustive in the potential ways
	that zone data can be divided up, it should be sufficient to
	illustrate the potential ways in which zone data can be
	controlled by multiple entities.</t>

	<t>The end result of all of these strategies, however, will be
	the same: a live zone containing DNSSEC related resource
	records.  Many of the above strategies are merely different
	ways of preparing a zone for serving.  A management solution
	that includes support for managing DNSSEC zone data may wish
	to take into account these potential management scenarios.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
